So today's דף daf *daf* officially we should be on כז *Chof
Zayin*, but we're a close דף *daf* behind so we're on כו
*Chof Vav*.
And we are in the middle of a discussion of things that
the, for which people or which situation a person has to do
קריעה keriah. *kriya* and also a קריעה keriah *kriya* that cannot be
sewn up. So we are in the middle of a discussion about
hearing God's name being blasphemed, ברכת השם birchas hashem, *birchas hashem*, and
we are on כו עמוד א *Chof Vav Amud Aleph*. We pick
up with
where
were we? תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan: *Tanu Rabanan*. 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, 7 lines down on the wide lines. There's an asterisk
by it, end of the line, תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan: *Tanu Rabanan*
or, okay. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan: *Tanu Rabanan*, our rabbis taught. אחד
השומע echad hashome'ah *Echad hashome'a*,
whether somebody hears the God's name being blasphemed, ואחד השומע מפי השומע
*v'echad hashome'a mi'pi hashome'a*, if a person hears it being repeated.
Now, presumably that means not just a report that it happened, but
an actual literal repetition of it. An actual literal repetition of it.
Now, who's supposed to actually literally repeat it and say the words
again? But the, if you look at תוספות Tosafot, *Tosfos*, he says,
פירש בתוספות כגון מן העדים שאומרים זה *pirish b'Tosfos kegon min ha'edim
she'omrim zeh*. So if a person, if they testify against someone, and
therefore they have to actually repeat what the person said, so they
wind up repeating the blaspheming again. חייב לקרוע *Chayav likro'a*. Is obligated
to do קריעה keriah. *kriya*. והעדים אינם חייבים לקרוע *Veha'edim einam chayavim
likro'a*, now when the witnesses repeat it, presumably that's when everybody else
heard it because it was being repeated, they don't have to do
a קריעה keriah *kriya* again שכבר קרעו בשעת ששמעו *she'kevar kar'u b'sha'as
sheshamu*.
They heard when they initially heard this, they heard the blaspheming taking
place. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, בשעת ששמעו מאי הוה? הא
קא שמעי השתא. *b'sha'as sheshamu mai hava? Haksha'ami hashta.* So okay, who
cares that they heard it once? They're hearing it again now from
their own lips. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, no, לא סלקא
דעתך *lo salkas daiteich*, that doesn't make sense, meaning that you would
make, that you would say that. דכתיב Dich-tiv, *Dichsiv*, because the verse
says, ויהי כשמוע המלך חזקיהו *vayehi kishmo'a hamelech Chizkiyahu* when the king
חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu* heard, right, this is about the story that we mentioned
before, right, about the people who came back and testified to this
act that רבשקה *Ravshakeh* did that he blasphemed God's name. So when
חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu* heard it, ויקרע את בגדיו *vayikra es begadav* and he
rent his garments. So you see, המלך קרע kera והם לא קרעו
*hamelech kara veheim lo kar'u*. So the king rent his garments but
the people that were repeating it did not. It says they came
with rent garments, it doesn't say that they rent their garments again.
Okay. ולא מתאחי מנלן *V'lo mis'achi minalan*? How do you know that
the rending of these garments under these situations, whether going all the
way back to what we discussed yesterday, whether it was the death
of a נשיא *nasi* or אב בית דין *av beis din* or
national tragedy, or this case of ברכת השם *birchas hashem*, how do
you know that it's not sewn up? מנלן *Minalan*? So אתיא קריעה
keriah. קריעה kria? *asya kriya kriya*, we make a גזירה שוה *gzeira
shava*, we learned before by mother and father and a רבי *rebbi*
that it's not torn up. We learned that from the story about
אליהו *Eliyahu* and אלישע *Elisha*. So here too it says תקרע *tikra*,
so it's a גזירה שוה *gzeira shava*. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* points
out if it's based on that, anytime that you do קריעה kriah.
*kriya*, we would say don't sew it up because of a גזירה
שוה *gzeira shava*. So if you look at this little תוספות Tosafot
*Tosfos*, it says אתיא קריעה kriah. תימא אם כן נילף כל קריעות
kriot כל קריעות שלא יתאחו *asya kriya teima im kein neileif kol
kriyos, kol kriyos shelo yis'achu*. Anytime you do קריעה kriah. *kriya*, don't
sew it up because it always says קריעה kriah. *kriya*, right? So
how do you get to choose which ones yes? He says, where
were we? לא יתאחו ושמא לא מסתברא ליה *Lo yis'achu v'shema lo
mistavra lei*.
Which basically, that doesn't make sense to apply it other ways. Which
basically means that חז"ל *Chazal* had an understanding from the beginning which
things were appropriate to sew up and which were not and they,
so they chose which ones to say applied this rule of not
sewing up. So I find that that's a fascinating little תוספות Tosafot.
*Tosfos* because certainly in, you know, ישיבות *yeshivas*, they tend to teach
it like all of the דרשות *drashos* are like totally mechanical. But
obviously they're not always mechanical, you got this extra thing, that tells
you this. But how do you determine which, what, what point that
extra little letter's supposed to be teaching you? Right, I mean, so
there's obviously like decisions in every single step of the process in
terms of how you're applying it and how, and what its implications
are. So anyway, תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* here basically says, yeah, we should
basically say anything you don't sew up, what are we going to
apply this principle to? The ones that make sense to apply it
to. Okay, so now back to the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. It says...
Jack, we've just got a subjective.
Yeah, clearly. Right. So now but also look, there's a whole question
here about how much are we doing real דרשות *drashos*? Are we
saying that this is all דאורייתא *de'oraisa* like these פסוקים pesukim *psukim*
are, I mean so far pretty much all the פסוקים *psukim* have
been from נביאים *Nevi'im*, right? Not one of them from the תורה
*Torah*. Right? So how much are we understanding that this is like
telling us a biblical obligation of קריעה kriah *kriya* or it's just,
you know,
informing us of a practice, is it rabbinic like same by אבילות
aveilus, *aveilus*, right? There's a lot of פסוקים *psukim* floating around but
according to some ראשונים Rishonim *rishonim* it's all rabbinic. All right, now
again, that's, you know, here it's worth again pointing out like by
the קריעה kriah *kriya* aspect, by rabbinic it might mean in sense
of a technical legal obligation, the fact that this would have existed
as a practice and as an institution, I mean that's clear about
אבילות aveilus. *aveilus* and it's... clear about קריעה kriah? aspect, by rabbinic
it might mean in sense of a technical legal obligation. The fact
that this existed as a practice and as an institution, I mean,
that's clear about אבלות avelut and it's clear about קריעה. kriah. So,
you know, again, it's interesting here, how much are we sort of
learning out what the practice is and how much are we learning
out a technical legal obligation?
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara gets back.
ספר תורה שנשרף מנלן? Sefer Torah she-nisraf minalan? How do we know
when a ספר תורה Sefer Torah is burnt that one does קריעה
kriah and does not sew it up? דכתיב, the verse says, ויהי
כקרוא יהודי שלוש דלתות וארבע, Vayhi kikhro Yehudi shalosh delatot ve-arba, when
the Jew read three sections or four, three verses or four. This
is about the reading of the מגילת איכה Megilat Eicha that ירמיה
Yirmiyah had written, presumably it was the מגילת איכה. Megilat Eicha. ויקרעה
בתער הסופר, Vay-ikraeha be-ta'ar hasofer, and the king tore it with a
like basically with a barber's razor וישלך אל
האש אשר אל האח, Vay-ashlech el ha-esh asher el ha-ach, and threw
it on the fire, which was like by the furnace. מאי שלוש
דלתות וארבע? Mai shalosh delatot ve-arba? What does it mean three or
four? אמרו ליה ליהויקים, Amru lei le-Yehoyakim, so they said to יהויקים,
Yehoyakim, כתב ירמיה ספר קינות, Katav Yirmiyah Sefer Kinot, ירמיה Yirmiyah wrote
a book of lamentations, presumably איכה. Eicha. אמר להו מאי כתיב ביה?
Amar lehu mai k-tiv beih? And now we're going to see that
that is exactly what
the גמרא Gemara understands it
to be
is איכה. Eicha. What's written in it? So איכה ישבה בדד, Eicha
yashvah vadad, how did the city, you know, dwell alone?
אמר להו אנא מלכא, Amar lehu ana malka, alright I'm the king,
nothing's going to happen to me.
אמרו ליה בכו תבכה בלילה, Amru lei bacho tivkeh ba-lailah, it cries
at night.
אנא מלכא, Ana malka, I'm a king, doesn't affect me. גלתה יהודה
מעוני, Galtah Yehudah me-oni, the entire, you know, Judah, Judea, will be
exiled from oppression.
אנא מלכא, Ana malka, I'm a king, won't happen to me. דרכי
ציון אבלות, Darchei Tziyon aveilot,
the ways of Zion are mourning, so there's no, nobody is traveling
on the roads. אנא מלכא, Ana malka, I'm a king, won't affect
me.
היו צריה לראש, Hayu tzareha lerosh, ah, its enemies are going to
be its rulers, right? Oh, אמר להו מאן אמרה? Amar lehu man
amrah? Says who?
So now he's worried because not him anymore. אמר להו מאן אמרה?
Amar lehu man amrah? Says who? כי ה' הוגה על רוב פשעיה,
Ki Hashem hogah al rov p-shaeha, God, you know, is sort of
doing this being processed, planned this because of all of its sins.
So מיד, Mi-yad, oh, God now is doing this to me? And
now it's going to affect me? So מיד קדר כל האזכרות שבה,
Mi-yad kadar kol ha-azkarot she-bah, he tore out all of the names
of God from the מגילה Megilah ושרפן באש, ve-sarfan ba-esh, and burnt
them in fire to get back at God.
So והיינו דכתיב, Ve-hainu dich-tiv, and that's why it says now going
back to the actual narrative about how they read the מגילה Megilah
in front of him and it says he burnt it. That was
a little sort of like digression, you know, about actual reading from
the book. והיינו דכתיב ולא פחדו ולא קרעו את בגדיהם, Ve-hainu dich-tiv
velo pachadu velo kar'u et bigdeihem, the people around did not fear
and they did not rend their garments. מכלל דבעו למקרע, Miklal di-vau
le-mikrah, so you see that the response is to do
קריעה. kriah Okay, now of course by this way it highlights the
fact that it was burning the שם השם, shem Hashem, which you
know means that it's not exactly about the, about it specifically focuses
on the שם השם, shem Hashem, not on the entire ספר. Sefer.
If you look again in תוספות, Tosafot קדר כל האזכרות, Kadar kol
ha-azkarot, תוספות Tosafot says תימא והא דקאמר בתער הסופר משמע כל המגילה,
Teimah ve-ha dik-amar be-ta'ar hasofer mashma kol ha-Megilah, the simple sense of
the פסוק pasuk is it was the entire מגילה. Megilah. ובירושלמי לא
גרסינן אזכרות, U-vi-Yerushalmi lo garsinan azkarot, and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it does
not say that it was דווקא davka the names of God that
he burnt, which would have reshaped, which would have, you know, sort
of
focused the concern, changed the focus of the concern. Okay, so now
back to the גמרא, Gemara so that's about a ספר תורה Sefer
Torah that was burnt. So the גמרא Gemara. says like this, אמר
ליה רב פפא לאביי, Amar lei Rav Papa le-Abaye, רב פפא Rav
Papa says to אביי, Abaye, אימא משום
שמועות רעות? Eima mishum shmuot raot? Maybe it's because of these terrible
reports, right? Because we said national tragedy, so this is talking about
how the entire people were going into exile, that's a national tragedy.
אמר ליה שמועות רעות בההיא שעתא מי הוו? Amar lei shmuot raot
be-hahi sha'ata mi havu? No, that was just a prediction. The tragic
events had not yet occurred. So you wouldn't קריעה kriah because of
the tragic event, it's only when tragic events have actually occurred, not
about something in the future, something that has already occurred. Okay. אמר
רבי חלבו אמר רב הונא הרואה ספר תורה שנקרע חייב לקרוע שתי
קריעות. Amar Rabbi Helbo Amar Rav Huna ha-roeh Sefer Torah she-nikrah chayav
likro shtei k-riot. If a person sees a ספר תורה Sefer Torah
that's torn, a person has to do two rending of the garments,
אחת על הגויל ואחת על הכתב, achat al ha-gevil ve-achat al ha-ketav,
one for the parchment and one for the script. שנאמר אחרי שרוף
המלך את המגילה ואת
הדברים. Shenemar acharei s-rof ha-melech et ha-Megilah ve-et ha-dvarim. After the king
burnt the actual מגילה, Megilah, the parchment, the scroll, and the words.
So the very words themselves, you know,
are part of the reason. It's obviously it's not just the physical
embodiment of it, which seems to be the point that it's not
just the, you know, the physical embodiment, but it's the complete as
if the attempt to destroy the content of it and the words
of it is also at least as an equal reason to do
קריעה. kriah Right.
Would this apply as הלכה halachah if the ספר sefer were torn
on the seam where it's sewn?
No, and not only that, let's take a look at the next
at the next story which will partially answer that from a different
perspective.
So, but that's a good point, what if it's torn and if
it's not and if it's not burnt? And what if it's only
the parchment without the without the words? Right. רבי אבא ורב הונא
בר חייא. Rabbi Abba v'Rav Hunah bar Chiya. So now we're going
to hear a story that partially answers that. רבי אבא ורב הונא
בר חייא הוי יתבי קמיה דרבי אבא Rabbi Abba v'Rav Hunah bar
Chiya havay yaisvay kamey deRabbi Abba was or so that's doesn't exactly
fit such as was רבי אבי Rabbi Avi was it רבי אבא
Rabbi Abba was in front of רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba. Let's see.
There's a switch of the גרסא girsa here.
There's two
people? Two רבי אבא? Rabbi Abba?
No, they take out הוי יתבי קמיה דרבי אבא. havay yaisvay kamey
deRabbi Abba. It just has קמיה דרבי אבא. kamey deRabbi Abba. Okay.
So רבי אבא Rabbi Abba got up, בעי לאתנויי, ba'ee l'itnuyay, and
he had to go to the bathroom. שקלי לטוטפתיה, shaklay l'totaftei,
so he took off his תפילין, tefillin, because obviously they were sitting
all day wearing תפילין, tefillin, and ואחתיה אבי סדיא v'achasay abei sadi
and he put it on his like on his like scarf. אתא
בת נעמיתא, asay bat ne'amisa,
an ostrich came, I think that's what בת נעמיתא bat ne'amisa is.
Is that what they translated? Ostrich? An ostrich came, the ostriches eat
everything.
בעי למבלעיה, b'ai
l'mivlay,
so and it wanted to swallow it. אמר, amar, he said, השתא
חייבינן לשתי קריעות, hashta chayvinan l'shtay kriot, so now I presumably it
didn't swallow it. It sounds like, now I would have been obligated
to have done two קריעות had it swallowed my תפילין, tefillin, because
it would have destroyed it. It's like destroying a מגילה, megillah, you
know, a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So now it's interesting. It's not
an entire ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, what constitutes a ספר תורה? Sefer
Torah? But actually it's got שם השם shem Hashem if you want
to have that emphasis from the previous discussion. אמר ליה, amar lei,
so רב הונא בר חייא Rav Huna bar Chiya said back to
him, מנלך הא, minalach ha, where do you get that idea that
you'd have to do קריעה? kriah. והא בדידי הוה עובדא, veha bidiidi
havay uvda, you know what? The same thing happened to me that
an ostrich swallowed mine.
I don't know. Anyway, or something similar happened to me. ואתאי לקמיה
דרב מתנה, va'asai l'kamey deRav Matna, I came to רב מתנה, Rav
Matna, ולא הוה ידע, velo hava yadei, he didn't know the answer.
אתאי לקמיה דרב יהודה, asai l'kamey deRav Yehuda, he came to רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, ואמר לי ve'amar lei and he said to me,
הכי אמר שמואל, hachi amar Shmuel, this is what שמואל Shmuel said,
לא אמרו אלא בזרוע וכמעשה שהיה, lo amru ela b'zroa uke'ma'aseh shehayah,
that's only when it was done like with violence, with force, and
like the story that happened, where it was like, you know, sort
of willfully burnt and destroyed by, you know, as opposed to here
where it's like a natural occurrence. Now what's the significance of זרוע?
zroa? So רש"י, Rashi, רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom here
says בזרוע b'zroa means שאין יכול להצילו, she'ein yachol l'hatzilo,
that there would have been no way even if somebody had been
present to try to save it, as opposed to the ostrich, and
you know if you're there you can chase the ostrich away, but
you can't chase a king away. Which is interesting, like why does
it care if somebody could or couldn't have saved it? At the
end of the day it was destroyed, right? So תוספות Tosafot, here
quotes the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. He says בירושלמי גרס לא אמרו אלא בזרוע
ששרפם מלך ישראל בזרוע, b'Yerushalmi garas lo amru ela b'zroa shesarafam melech
Yisrael b'zroa,
right?
Which seems like it's not just so much it couldn't be saved,
but it seems like it was like a willful, you know, act
from a power, from somebody who's in power. So it's much more
of a sense of like a willful destroying of this and obviously,
you know, a denigration of it.
So an act of violence done to it. Okay. ערי יהודה מנלן,
arei Yehuda minalan,
so that's about a ספר תורה Sefer Torah and exactly what the
parameters of ספר תורה Sefer Torah is interesting from this discussion of
תפילין. tefillin. Now,
right, okay, but it could still be an act of
violence, maybe, according to the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. ערי יהודה מנלן, arei Yehuda
minalan, where do you know about the cities of Judea, presumably seeing
them in their destroyed state, in their state of destruction? The verse
says, ויבאו אנשים משכם משלו ומשמרון, vayavo'u anashim miShchem miShilo umiShomron,
and this is after, you know, in the immediate aftermath of the
destruction, people came from שכם Shchem and שלו Shilo and שמרון, Shomron,
שמונים איש, shmonim ish, 80 people, מגולחי זקן, meguchei zakan, they shaved
a beard, וקרועי בגדים, ukruei begadim, and rent garments, ומתגודדים, umitgodedim, and
which you're not supposed to do, right? Which like lacerated their flesh.
ומנחה ולבנה בידם להביא בית השם, umincha ulevona beyadam lehavi beit Hashem,
and with a, you know, with these various sacrifices to bring to
the בית השם, beit Hashem, which of course had,
so in the wake of the destruction, which is obviously a whole
fascinating phenomenon. אמר רבי חלבו אמר עולא ביראה אמר רבי אלעזר, amar
Rabbi Chelbo amar Ulla biri amar Rabbi Elazar, okay, so that's the
end, that is that is the verse. So you see that what
they did as a response to the destroying of the cities was
that they did these tremendous acts of mourning. Of course it was
quite excessive, which the גמרא Gemara is going to get back to.
Okay, but let's take a look, let's keep let's go a little
bit further.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
one minute, we're
learning one of the things that you're supposed to do from the
other...
no, so take a look at תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says like
this, משכם משלו לא שייך הכא למיפרך ואימא עד דאיכא תלת, miShchem
miShilo lo shayach hacha l'mifrach ve'eima ad d'ika tlat,
maybe you need like all three,
שכם. Shchem. and שומרון Shomron to all be destroyed, right? So he
says no.
That’s not even a הוה אמינא hava amina because presumably each I
don’t know because presumably each one of the people was from a
different city. So anyway, אבל קצת קשיא דאימר מילתא יתירתא היא. aval
ktzat kashya d'eimar milta yeseira hi.
But what is problematic is not that you need all three cities
to be destroyed, but maybe this is excessive. דמגלחי זקן ומתגודדים כתיב
בהאי קרא d'megalchei zakan umitgoddim ktiv b'hai kra because like being shaved,
you’re supposed to not shave your hair and lacerated flesh. דשמן דלא
שייך למימר
דלא ניתנייה כלל. d'shamen d'lo shayach l'meimar d'lo neitanya klal. אלא Ella
so basically תוספות says no because basically they wanted to learn something
out of the verse. So therefore, rather than reject the whole verse
they right again sort of choosing what to learn. We learn the
idea of קריעה. kriah But obviously here there is this problem that
they are clearly what they are doing is excessive. Okay, so אמר
רבי חלבו אמר עולא ביראה אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Chelbo amar
Ula Birah amar Rabbi Elazar but we're choosing what to learn from
it. אמר רבי חלבו אמר עולא ביראה אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi
Chelbo amar Ula Birah amar Rabbi Elazar back to the גמרא. Gemara
הרואה ערי יהודה בחורבנם אומר Haro'eh arei yehuda bechurbanam omer somebody sees
the cities of Judea in their destroyed state, so again what you
also could have said is maybe only if you experience them being
destroyed not if they've been destroyed for like decades and centuries, right?
That also it’s like it’s old news. I know you're seeing it
and it’s a new your experience, but again to learn from the
verse that if you see it as something after it's happened many
many years ago is also a huge חידוש chiddush not based on
the verse. So anyway, but here he's now saying it very explicitly
that you don't have to experience them being destroyed if you see
them in their destroyed state, אומר omer you say עריך קדשך היו
מדבר Areich kodshecha hayu midbar your holy cities have become like the
wilderness וקורע v'kore'ah
and then you do קריעה. Kria ירושלים בחורבנה Yerushalayim bechurbana if you
see ירושלים Yerushalayim in its destroyed state אומר omer ציון מדבר הייתה
ירושלים שממה Tziyon midbar hayta Yerushalayim shemama
Zion became a wilderness,
ירושלים Yerushalayim a desolate place וקורע v'kore'ah and you do קריעה. Kria
בית המקדש בחורבנו Beit Hamikdash bechurbano if you see the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash in its destroyed state אומר omer בית קדשנו ותפארתנו אשר
הללוך אבותינו היה לשרפת אש וכל מחמדנו היו לחרבה. Beit kodsheinu v'tifartenu
asher hilalucha avotenu haya lisrefat esh v'chol machmadenu hayu l'charba.
Obviously all of these are פסוקים from ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. The house of
our holy house and our glory which our forefathers had praised has
been to something that has been destroyed by fire
and all of our desirous things have become to destruction וקורע v'kore'ah
and do קריעה. Kria And this actually is brought down in the
שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. I'm actually one of the, this is actually
brought down not on הלכות אבילות Hilchot Aveilut but it's at the
end of הלכות תענית Hilchot Ta'anit where it deals with all of
the things that because the main reasons for the fast days are
related to the destruction of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. קורע על
מקדש Kore'ah al mikdash
we’ll talk about these in a minute. קורע על מקדש ומוסיף על
ירושלים Kore'ah al mikdash umosif al Yerushalayim a person does the קריעה
Kria on the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and then when he sees
ירושלים Yerushalayim he adds to the קריעה Kria of course. הי דלפני
hei d'lifnei how does he why how did that order work out?
So the גמרא Gemara says רמינהו אדתניא raminihu ad'tanya אחד השומע ואחד
הרואה echad hashome'ah v'echad haro'eh whether a person heard now presumably this
is not heard the news of the destruction, right? Not the heard
the fact that they were destroyed one imagines that that’s not or
if one sees it. So again it’s funny, right, because the original
framing was after it had immediately occurred and that’s where אחד השומע
is coming from. But now we’re including הרואה haro'eh which is having
seen them in their destroyed state even from many many years ago.
כיון שהגיע להר הצופים keivan she-higia l'har hatzofim so whether you heard
that it was destroyed
those are two different things one is it was destroyed now the
other is you see it later.
Yes, okay. So that’s number one. Now כיון שהגיע להר הצופים keivan
she-higia l'har hatzofim and this presumably is when you are seeing it
to when at what page when you see it does one do
קריעה? Kria When you get to הר הצופים Har Hatzofim okay so
קורע kore'ah then you’re able to see, see ירושלים Yerushalayim so you
do קריעה. Kria וקורע על מקדש בפני עצמו ועל ירושלים בפני עצמה
v'kore'ah al mikdash bifnei atzmo v'al ירושלים בפני עצמה Yerushalayim bifnei atzma
and you do קריעה Kria for the מקדש Mikdash by itself and
ירושלים Yerushalayim by itself. So here we’ve got a two, well one
explicit contradiction which isn’t the one you were probably thinking which has
that you don’t do one קריעה Kria, and add to it you're
קורע kore'ah on the מקדש Mikdash and you add to ירושלים Yerushalayim
but you do a separate קריעה Kria for each. So that’s the
real focus that the גמרא Gemara, is making. It’s not one קריעה
Kria, with adding but it’s a separate קריעה. Kria But also the
simple sense here is that you’re first coming in through ירושלים Yerushalayim
which anyway you could have asked even without the ברייתא. baraita. So
let’s see what the גמרא Gemara answers. So the גמרא Gemara says
לא קשיא lo kashya it’s not difficult. הא דפגע במקדש ברישא והא
דפגע בירושלים ברישא ha d'paga b'mikdash breisha v'ha d'paga b'yerushalayim breisha if
first a person encounters the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash without ירושלים Yerushalayim
he was airdropped in
okay? Doesn’t explain how רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom sort of says how
אפילו תימא afilu teima basically exactly it was like brought in a
box. הא דפגע במקדש ברישא דהיינו דנכנס בירושלים בשידה תיבה ומגדל ha
d'paga b'mikdash breisha d'hainu d'nichnas b'yerushalayim b'shida teivah umigdal he was brought
in a box. Okay so you have to imagine that anyway somehow
magically a person first was born in the saw the מקדש Mikdash
before
never left his house until he anyway I guess. Anyway all right.
Then he does קריעה kriah on the מקדש Mikdash and since the
מקדש Mikdash is the more severe one he can add to it
for ירושלים. Yerushalayim. If a normal person is going through ירושלים... Yerushalayim...
to the מקדש, Mikdash, he does one קריעה kriah, for ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
and then because מקדש Mikdash is more severe, it should not just
be secondary to the קריעה kriah that was already done for ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, so that requires an independent קריעה kriah for מקדש. Mikdash. Okay.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: Our Rabbis taught. שולל, Sholal, מלל, Malal, ואקט,
v'Oket, ולעשות כמין סולמות, v'la'asos k'min sulamos, אבל לא לאחותם. aval lo
l'achotom.
So all of these we were saying are not just things you
have to do קריעה kriah. for, but that you do not fully
sew them up, like you don't reweave them. So here it's saying
yes, you can sew them in different ways, you can but you
cannot really do what's called איחוי, ichoy, which is a completely making
it whole. שולל, Sholal, מלל, Malal, all of these are like types
of loose types of stitches or various types of threading it together,
but not a כמין סולמות k'min sulamos like a ladder is like
having like rungs so it's not tight like there are stitches that
are holding the two halves together, but they're well spaced from one
another. Various types of ways of stitching it together you can do,
but not to do
a tight stitch and really make it whole.
אמר רב חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: ובאיחוי אלכסנדרי, u'v'ichoy Alexandri, and even
the type of a stitching that's problematic is only the Alexandrian stitching,
which is really one of making it whole again. One imagines that
it's close to like a reweaving of the garment. תנו רבנן: Tanu
rabanan, הקורע מתוך השולל ומתוך המלל ומתוך האקט ומתוך הסולמות, HaKorei mitoch
haSholal u'mitoch haMalal u'mitoch haOket u'mitoch haSulamos, so all these words parallel
the words we had before of acceptable ways of restitching it. So
if a person went ahead and restitched
a קריעה kriah with these various stitches, which we have just learned
before are not considered to have made it whole, and then a
person goes ahead and does a קריעה kriah to rerend the garment,
to break those stitches, לא יצא. lo yatza. One does not fulfill
their obligation because the whole point is that those types of stitches
do not make it whole. So one did not do a קריעה
kriah, on a whole garment. One did a קריעה kriah. on something
that was already considered to be rend. However, מתוך האיחוי, mitoch ha'ichoy,
if a garment had been
really rewoven, restitched together, now again, let's say it wasn't something that
you're not allowed to do איחוי ichoy for, it was for another
relative in which you're allowed to do איחוי, ichoy, or it was
just something that accidentally tore. It wasn't an act of קריעה, kriah
the garment tore, and somebody had restitched it in a tight way
to the point where they did this איחוי ichoy which was considered
now that it's whole. So now you've got a whole garment and
then you do a קריעה kriah. on a whole garment, then יצא,
yatza, you fulfill your obligation. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, and
here too רב חסדא Rav Chisda says: ובאיחוי אלכסנדרי, u'v'ichoy Alexandri, only
if it's the real Alexandrian איחוי. ichoy. So that's a חומרא chumra
and a קולא, kula, right? When it comes to having rent the
garment for father or mother, it's only prohibited if you do the
איחוי אלכסנדרי, ichoy Alexandri, this really full stitching and weave. When it
comes to the question about is a person יוצא yotzei if they
rend something that's been rewoven, then it's only if it's been rewoven
in this very full stitching, this Alexandrian איחוי. ichoy. Okay. תנו רבנן:
Tanu rabanan.
you do the same spot and you do another spot.
Right, it's the same spot, correct.
תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan, רשאי להופכו למטה ולאחותו. Rashai l'hofcho l'mata v'l'achoto.
Now here's a shocking thing. A person can actually turn the garment
not inside out but like upside down. I mean if you want
to imagine it's like a pretty much like a straight tunic, I
guess one could imagine you've got to flip it over and you
do enough sewing on the top.
Well maybe it is inside out.
Inside out because it would not... no, למטה, l'mata, להופכו למטה. l'hofcho
l'mata.
So then you can sew it up because now that's interesting because
then it becomes a different part of the garment, it becomes the
hem. It no longer sort of represents in the way the garment
has been reshaped, it no longer represents the קריעה, kriya right? It's
just some tear at the hem. Right, you're not יוצא yotzei קריעה
kriya at the hem, so it no longer is in the place
of the garment that it represents the tear. And therefore since it
no longer has that weight, it can now be sewn up, which
is pretty funny because you could say then what allows you to
turn it upside down and to change, transform it in that way?
But I mean I think you know this goes
back to the point that Seth made yesterday that obviously the symbolism
of totally sewing it up, like making it whole, something that can
never be made whole. So if you didn't, this is sort of
like an indirect way because you never directly said I'm going to
make whole
this rend, this symbolic rend. It's just it's not being that rend
because it became something on the hem of the garment.
So fascinatingly that's according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma allowed. רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
says אוסר לאחותו. oser l'achoto. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar forbade it. And as you can see by the little letter,
that's how we rule. So no, I'm sorry, wherever it's located you
cannot sew it up. Okay,
to do this tight weaving of it. Okay, שם, shem, not sister.
וכשם שהמוכר אסור לאחותו, u'keshem she'hamocher asur l'achoto, now the same way
the seller cannot, the person who did the rending, כך הלוקח אסור
לאחותו. kach ha'loke'ach asur l'achoto. The one who purchase it, it has
to remain this way that as we would say in Brisker terminology
it's a הלכה halacha not just in the גברא gavra but in
the חפצא. cheftza. Okay? So the object no matter who's handling it,
that has to be the status. That one does it like leaves
to respect that status of the garment.
Now there's an interesting question, ולפיכך ulifichach and therefore, מוכר צריך להודיע
ללוקח. mocher tzarich lehodia lalokeach. If you sell it, you have to
tell the person, you know, you should realize this was a קריעה
kriya that was done, you know, for whatever purpose, repaired or whatever,
and therefore it's not allowed to be sewn up. Okay, so again
תוספות asks the fascinating question, like he asked a similar question by
ברכת השם, what about a non-Jew? כך הלוקח אסור לאחותו. kach halokeach
assur le'achoto. If we look at תוספות, it says לא שמעתי אם
מותר למוכרו לנכרי. lo shamati im mutar lemochro lenochri. Can you sell
it to a non-Jew? Right, so is it that you, the one
who did this, have to make sure that the garment is never,
you know, fully sewn, and therefore it doesn't matter who's doing the
sewing? Or is it that no, since the other person is a
Jew and follows הלכה, halacha, they have similar types of rules that
apply to them? So he says, נהי דלוקח אסור לאחותו אם הוא
נכרי מותר. nehi delokeach assur le'achoto im hu nochri mutar. Maybe we
should say that if he's a non-Jew, it's allowed. אע"פ דמוכר צריך
להודיע ללוקח היינו כדי שלא יבא לוקח לידי איסור. af al pi
de'mocher tzarich lehodia lalokeach hainu kedei shelo yavo lokeach liyedei issur. When
the seller has to tell the purchaser, is it because the seller
is responsible to make sure that wherever the garment might be it
never gets sewn up, or is it because he's responsible for the
halakhic observance of the purchaser? And the purchaser only if he's a
Jew has to follow the הלכה. halacha. Okay, אבל אינו חושש אם
יתפרנו הנכרי, aval eino choshesh im yitperennu hanochri, but maybe we shouldn't
be concerned. He says, ולכאורה היה מותר, ulichora haya mutar, it would
seem that it might be permissible. Then if you look at the
side, the asterisk says, ובמסכת שמחות סוף פרק ט' איתא דאסור. u've'masechet
semachot sof perek tet ita de'assur. But in מסכת שמחות, Masechet Semachot,
which is minor Tannaic collections of areas about אבילות, aveilus it actually
deals with this and it says that it's forbidden. Okay, but actually
anyway that's fascinating in terms of how much is it the fully
a status of the חפצא. cheftza. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan. back to
the גמרא, Gemara about eight lines down. תחלת קריעה טפח. tchilas kriah
tefach. The beginning of the קריעה, kriya. how far does the קריעה
kriya have to be? It has to be a טפח. tefach. Now
we've talked by אביו ואמו aviv ve'imo was עד שיגלה לבו, ad
sheyegale libo, until the heart is exposed, but let's assume now we're
talking not about אביו ואמו. aviv ve'imo. It has to be a
טפח. tefach. ותוספת שלש. ve'tosefet shalosh. Now what if, חס ושלום, chas
ve'shalom, what happens at שלש אצבעות? shalosh etzbaot? What if after somebody
heard like a brother died they did קריעה kriya and then in
the middle of the שבעה shiva they heard that a sister died?
So then they would do, they wouldn't have to do another, we
talked before, right, about whether if you start on the המקדש hamikdash
you can add to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But if you start on ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, you have to do a separate one for the המקדש. hamikdash.
So presumably if the second one is of greater weight, it gets
its own קריעה. kriya. So we're going to come up to that,
right, because we're saying ירושלים Yerushalayim one and מקדש mikdash separate, you
would have let's say a sibling would be one and then a
parent would be separate, they could not, it could not be an
addition. But if things are at the same level, it could be
an addition to what was already done. So a person did a
קריעה kriya of a טפח tefach on let's say one sibling and
then heard about another one and therefore they add, they don't have
to, they can add, number one. And they don't have to do
the full amount, they can just add שלש טפחים shalosh tefachim because
then it just, you know, the end result, even though the act
of קריעה kriya it tore less of the garment, but the garment
itself is fully, you know, is fully torn because it already had
a טפח tefach to begin with. So
that's the first opinion, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said. רבי יהודה אומר תחלת קריעה שלש אצבעות
ותוספת כל שהוא. Rabbi Yehuda omer tchilas kriah shalosh etzbaot ve'tosefet kol
shehu. The beginning only has to be שלש אצבעות, shalosh etzbaot, not
even a full טפח, tefach, which is funny because before we had
been saying a טפח, tefach, but the addition can be even a
small amount. Again because it results in a torn garment of appropriate
size. אמר עולא הלכה כרבי מאיר בקריעה. Amar Ulla halacha ke'Rabbi Meir
bikriah. We rule like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir by the initial קריעה,
kriya which is a טפח, tefach, which is what we've said until
now. והלכה כרבי יהודה בתוספת, ve'halacha ke'Rabbi Yehuda betosefet, we rule like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda by the תוספת tosefet that it is a
little addition. And for the reason I said, the act doesn't have
to do an act of tearing a טפח, tefach, even a small
tearing as long as it results in a significant enough torn garment.
So once the garment already was torn a טפח, tefach, even a
little small additional tearing would count for a second אבילות. aveilus, תניא
נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly. רבי יוסי אומר תחלת
קריעה טפח ותוספת כל שהוא. Rabbi Yossi omer techilat kriah tefach ve'tosefet
kol shehu. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi here now says this compromised
position, the beginning is a full טפח, tefach, not שלש אצבעות, shalosh
etzbaot, three fingers width, but the addition is only a small amount.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan, Now you might be asking don't we always
go by the more lenient opinion, so hold on the גמרא Gemara
is going to get to that. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan our rabbis
taught. אמרו לו מת אביו. amru lo met aviv. Somebody was informed
that his father died. וקרע, ve'kara, and he did קריעה. kriya מת
בנו, met beno, and then afterwards he was informed that his son
died, I mean it's tragic these circumstances. והוסיף, ve'hosif,
and then did an addition because again if the second קריעה kriya?
is of equal or lesser weight, I mean sorry to frame it
that way but that's the הלכתית halakhic status here, then it can
be added to the first קריעה. kriya. So therefore in this case,
you know, again as we've mentioned before clearly the death of a
child is much more tragic, you know, in most cases than the
death of a parent, but הלכתית halachit the death of a parent
has this weightier status because of כיבוד אב ואם. kibbud av va'eim.
So therefore this one because it is no... not a parent can
be an addition to the קריעה kriya of the
parent. So the person did the קריעה kriya on the parent and
then did an additional קריעה kriya on another, on his child. In
that case והוסיף, v'hosif, תחתון מתאחה עליון אינו מתאחה. tachton mit'acheh elyon
eino mit'acheh.
This is like a hybrid קריעה. kriya, So the bottom part, the
additional part that was torn, has a status of a קריעה kriya
that can be sewn up, and the top part, which is for
the parent, for the father, cannot be sewn up, so the קריעה
kriya, itself has two statuses based on which section we're talking about,
the top section or the bottom section. מת בנו וקרע, meis beno
v'kara, just wait. The son died and he did קריעה. kriya מת
אביו והוסיף. meis aviv v'hosif. And now it says the father died
and he added on it. Now that's going to be interesting because
the idea that you're allowed to do a הוספה, hosafa, as I've
been saying, that should not logically have been the case, so we'll
get back to that. עליון מתאחה תחתון אינו מתאחה. elyon mit'acheh tachton
eino mit'acheh.
So the top one, which is for the son, can be sewn
up, the bottom, the additional, which is for the father, cannot be
sewn up. מת אביו מת אמו מת אחיו מת אחותו, meis aviv
meis imo meis achiv meis achoto, okay, which is like horrific, right?
So the whole family has died. קורע קרע אחד לכולן. korea kera
echad l'chulan. So apparently he heard about this at one time, so
in this case it's one קריעה kriya for everyone. You don't have
to, a person does not have to do הוספות hosafot unless they're
sequential. חס ושלום chas v'shalom in this case, if it's all at
the same time, one can be for everyone. רבי יהודה בן בתירה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer, now Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira says
more in line with what we said before about ירושלים Yerushalayim and
the מקדש: Mikdash: על כולן קרע אחד על אביו ואמו קרע אחד.
al kulan kera echad al aviv v'imo kera echad. No, you have
to separate, a person would have to separate the קריעה kriya, for
father and mother and the קריעה kriya for the others. לפי שאין
מוסיפין על קרע אביו ואמו lefi she-ein mosifin al kera aviv v'imo
because you cannot, you know, do add on the tearing for אביו
ואמו. aviv v'imo. So, so what does that mean? So, מאי טעמא,
mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, לפי שאינן בתוספת lefi she-einan b'tosefet because you're not
supposed to add to them, which is not very helpful because, okay,
why? Because you can't. What's that supposed to say? So there's a
whole תוספות trying to figure out exactly what that means, and but
anyway, we won't sort of try to, it's a little complicated what
תוספות does to try to explain how that's actually adding something. But
here he's actually saying that there has to be, that there has
to be a separate one. Hold on, I think I said it
wrong a minute ago because, right, I think I said it incorrectly
because the הלכה halacha was, the הלכה halacha by ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I'm
sorry, by ירושלים Yerushalayim and the מקדש Mikdash is that if a
person starts with the מקדש, Mikdash, they can add for ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
If you start with the more serious one, I think I'm sorry,
I apologize, I think I reversed it. Start with the more serious
one, you can add for the less serious. You cannot do the
reverse. You cannot make the more serious one a, you know, secondary.
You can't start with the less serious and make the more serious
one like an add-on to that. That was what we know from
the מקדש Mikdash and ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I might have said that wrong
yesterday, so I apologize. So the case here according to this at
the end, the first opinion is that it doesn't matter, you can
always start with one and add the other, and then either the
top or the bottom could be sewn depending on which one was
for the father and mother and which one was not. That was
the first opinion. The second opinion was like we said by מקדש
Mikdash and ירושלים Yerushalayim that אביו ואמו, aviv v'imo, you know, have
to, no, it is different than what we said before. It is
different than what we said before. Before we said you can start
with the מקדש Mikdash and add for ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and here we're
saying, he's saying you start with אביו ואמו aviv v'imo and you
can't add to it. So it's actually different than we said before.
Here he's actually saying that if you start with אביו ואמו aviv
v'imo and you can't add to it even though by something like
מקדש Mikdash and ירושלים Yerushalayim you can. So it actually is different
than we said before. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, says שמואל, Shmuel, הלכה כרבי יהודה בן
בתירה. halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira. We rule like רבי יהודה בן
בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira that a person would have to do
a separate קריעה kriya. for mother and father and a separate one
for other relatives. ומי אמר שמואל הכי והאמר שמואל הלכה כדברי המיקל
באבל? U-mi amar Shmuel hachi v'ha-amar Shmuel halacha k'divrei ha-meikel b'avel? We
rule like the more lenient approach, and here it's requiring a separate
act of קריעה? kriya So the גמרא Gemara says, important statement here,
אבילות לחוד קריעה לחוד. aveilus lachud kriya lachud. There's a difference between
אבילות aveilus and קריעה. kriya. As we've been learning, קריעה kriya exists
even outside of the context of אבילות, aveilus. and קריעה kriya exists
even before אבילות aveilut. begins. Right? קריעה kriya exists at the moment
of death. I mean, again, we tend to postpone it and so
on, but הלכתית, halachically, קריעה, kriya you know, is a completely, is
a separate phenomenon from that of אבילות. Does anybody practice today to
your knowledge like upon hearing people will? Some people do. I mean,
that is the real הלכה, halacha, but, you know, again, very often
we just postpone it to the funeral. Yeah. Okay. So now עד
היכן הוא קורע? ad heichan hu korea? עד היכן קורע? ad heichan
korea? So how far does the קריעה kriya go? Meaning, we've already
said a טפח. tefach. We've said, although not here, but we've said
elsewhere that by אביו ואמו, aviv v'imo, עד שיגלה לבו. ad she-yigaleh
libo. to reveal the heart.
But here the question is different, since we are talking about the
sort of tragic circumstances of adding to a קריעה, kriya so the
question is at what stage would the קריעה kriya. have gone so
far, you know, that you can't continue to add to it? Like
a person would have to start a קריעה kriya, in another place
on the בגד. beged. Okay, so let's say somebody has to- because
yeah, at after that point it's no longer significant to be adding,
to be, you know, it's already like a completely torn in half,
so an act of tearing requires some sense of wholeness to proceed-
the act to be- to have the tearing have significance. עד היכן
הוא קורע? ad heichan hu korei? עד טיבורו, ad tiburo, until the
belly button. If it's rent all the way to the belly button,
somebody got out of hand, חס ושלום chas veshalom there were many
deaths, and then after that point you can't- a person couldn't do
an additional קריעה, kriya, you'd have to go to a different place
on the בגד. beged. ויש אומרים עד לבו, v'yesh omrim ad libo,
until the heart. אף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר, af
al pi she'ein raya ladavar zecher ladavar, although there's no proof, there's
a hint. שנאמר, shene'emar, the verse says: וקרעו לבבכם ואל בגדיכם, vekiru
levavchem ve'al bigdeichem, rend your hearts and not your garments. So somehow
that's a hint that, I don't know, that the rending of the
garments stops once the heart is exposed or something. הגיעו לטיבורו, hige'u
letiburo, back to the תנא קמא's tanna kamma position that it goes
to the belly button. If a person did so many rendings or
got out of hand with one rending, got to the belly button,
and now חס ושלום chas veshalom has to do another rending, מרחיק
שלש אצבעות, marchik shalosh etzbaot, so you move sort of horizontally three
finger widths, you know, to a side, וקורע, vekorei, and does another
קריעה kriya when- if that's needed. נתמלא מלפניו, nitmalei milfanav, so again,
these are so tragic, imagining these circumstances. If the garment is filled
with tears in the front of it, he's been moving שלש טפחים
shalosh tefachim and it's now filled with tears, מחזירו לאחוריו, machziro l'achorav,
then you reverse- he reverses it and then he has a new
front to his garment, what used to be the back. נתמלא מלמעלה,
nitmalei milma'ala, let's say all the top of the garment, front and
back, is filled with tears, הופכו מלמטה, hofcho milmata, so turn it
up- you know, upside down, and now that's- like we had before,
somehow you can reverse it so that the top becomes the hem
and the bottom becomes the top, and now there's more spaces to
do קריעה. kriya, That assumes a person basically has like one piece
of clothing. Yeah, well, that's true also. Or a very large wardrobe.
Or he didn't want to ruin more than one piece of clothing.
So how many- how many? Okay. Okay. והקורע מלמטה ומן הצדדים, vehakorei
milmata umin hatzdadim, and what was sort of implicit all along here,
if one does קריעה kriya from the bottom or from the sides,
לא יצא, lo yatza, it's not יוצא, yotzei, it has to be
from the top, from the neck of the garment. That's got some
symbolic significance. Why? That's the question. Significance also that it's opposite where
the heart is, but also, you know, it's more also- alright, it's
more visible. Okay. אלא שכהן פורם מלמטה, ela shekohein poreim milmata, but
a כהן גדול, kohein gadol, excuse me, who's not supposed to rend
the garment, can rend it below, דווקא davka because that's not considered
to be a rending of the garments for אבילות. Okay. פליגי בה
רב מתנא ומר עוקבא ותרווייהו משמיה דאבוה דשמואל. pleigi bah Rav Matna
uMar Ukva vetarvaihu mishemei d'avuha diShmuel. So רב מתנא ומר עוקבא, Rav
Matna uMar Ukva, both of them in the name of שמואל Shmuel
debated this, ולוי ומשמיה דשמואל, v'Levi umishemei diShmuel, and לוי Levi in
the name of שמואל. Shmuel. חד אמר: chad amar: כל שבעה קורע
לאחר שבעה מוסיף. kol shiva korei l'achar shiva mosif. או שבעה, o
shiva, a person who hears about- who's sitting שבעה shiva for one
relative and hears about the death of another, would do a- I'm
sorry, excuse me. Yeah, alright. Okay. So a person who's sitting- is
sitting שבעה shiva for one relative and hears about another one, so
we'll do actually a different קריעה. kriya Well, okay, but yeah, so
this is taking a different position about when the מוסיף mosif is
allowed. That during the- during the- during the first week of שבעה,
shiva, according to this, you have to do a different קריעה kriya
because the first קריעה kriya is still considered sort of to- well,
we'll see. וחד אמר, vechad amar, the other one says: כל לאחר
שבעה מוסיף. kol l'achar shiva mosif. After שבעה shiva you can add.
Now the logic here is the following: is that since after שבעה
shiva a certain amount, well, depending on mother and father or others,
but it's allowed to be sewn up. So since the original קרע
kera, can be sewn up now that שבעה shiva is over, so
to some degree it's considered to be, even if it has yet
to be sewn up, it's considered to be no longer its status
as being a full קרע, kera, right, as a full torn, because
it can be made whole now. And therefore doing an act of
קריעה kriya. is significant. But during the first week, when it's not
allowed to be sewn up, doing an act of קריעה kriya is
like it's already a קרע, kera what's the act of קריעה kriya.
that you're doing? But after the first week where it can be
repaired, it's significant now to be doing the קריעה kriya on something
that is standing to be repaired. That's- that's the first position. Again,
this is different than we said before, because Micah's right, before it
sounded like a person is just מוסיף mosif right away. And here
we're finding about that it's only after a certain time period where
the מוסיף mosif has significance. So let's take a look. וחד אמר,
vechad amar, the other one says: כל שלשים קורע. kol shloshim korei.
Same idea, but is even more strict about when another הוספה hosafa
can be done. Entire 30 days you have to do a- a
person would have to do a separate קריעה. kria Only לאחר שלשים
מוסיף. l'achar shloshim mosif. Only after 30 can it be added to,
is the first קרע kera. considered to some degree in a state
of being... repaired. מתקיף לה רב זירא matkif lah Rav Zeira or
רב זירא אקניס, Rav Zeira akneis, מאן דאמר כל שבעה קורע, man
d'amar kol shiva korei, אמאי? amai? The one who says that כל
שבעה kol shiva a person has to do a different קריעה, kria
why? דלא ניתן לשולב, delo nitan l'sholev, because during שבעה shiva they're
not allowed to sew it up. So therefore it's already a full,
full-powered קרע. kera So what does an adding on it mean? Adding
on it would not be significant. אלא הא דאמר מר, ela ha
d'amar mar, so according to that, if that's the logic why you
can't do הוספה hosafa during the first week because it's considered to
be a full, full קריעה, that which we taught האשה ששללה לאלתר
ha'isha sheshalala l'altar that a woman is allowed to sew it up
right away even during שבעה shiva because so as not to be
exposed, הכא נמי, hacha nami, so would you say that for a
woman she can do a הוספה hosafa during the first week? Because
for her the rend in the garment is considered fit to be
fixed even during the first week. It says no, התם משום כבוד
אשה. hatam mishum kavod isha. That's in order to respect her dignity,
but that's not because the the the tear sort of on its
own terms is really fit to be fixed. It's something we'll allow
for her dignity, but it's not something that's about the status of
the tear. The tear in terms of its own status is a
full tear and doing another קריעה on it would not be significant.
מאן דאמר כל שלשים, man d'amar kol shloshim, but now we see
the גמרא Gemara is exposed what the logic is. When the tear
cannot be repaired, it's not meaningful to to extend it. Only when
it's in a state of being repaired is it right that it's
no longer really fully a קרע kera. and then another act is
significant. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. מאן דאמר כל
שלשים קורע אמאי? man d'amar kol shloshim korei amai? דלא ניתן לאחותו.
delo nitan l'achoto. So the one that says all שלשים shloshim you
have to do a separate קריעה, why? Because the difference between שבעה
shiva and שלשים shloshim is after שבעה shiva you could sew it,
but after שלשים shloshim you can fully repair it. So at what
stage is the tear considered to be in a different step stage,
in a different state that it's meaningful to do a קריעה on
it? Once שבעה shiva is out and it can be sewn, or
only once שלשים shloshim is out and it can be fully repaired?
So he says the one who says שלשים shloshim wants it to
be in a state where it's fit to be fully repaired before
you can do an additional act of קריעה on it. So אלא
לאביו ולאמו, ela l'aviv u'l'imo, according to that logic for father and
mother דלא ניתנו לאחות לעולם delo nitnu l'achot l'olam that even after
שלשים shloshim a person is not able to repair it, הכא נמי,
hacha nami, would you say that you can't do a תוספת tosafat
on that? Now the answer might be yes, but the גמרא Gemara
assumes that you could do a person could do a a תוספת
tosafat on אביו ואמו aviv v'imo after שלשים. shloshim. So the גמרא
Gemara says התם משום כבוד אביו ואמו הוא. hatam mishum kavod aviv
v'imo hu. No, there it's somewhat like the opposite. Like in the
case by the woman, it was you're allowed the woman can sew
it up but in its own terms it's not deserving of being
sewn up, so therefore it's not meaningful to do a קרע. kera
Here by the אביו ואמו aviv v'imo it's the reverse. On its
own terms it's deserving to be sewn up, but in terms of
out of respect for mother and father we don't sew it up.
So since somehow the on its own terms it's deserving, to do
an act of קריעה on it after שלשים shloshim would be significant.
So this is quite fascinating, you can imagine that the בריסקרס Briskers
love this because it talks about like status of it as a
חפצא, cheftza, is it fit to be sewn up as opposed to
the the allowance for me to sew it up or not to
sew it up? And those are not exactly the same. But again
what's interesting here is not only as Michael pointed out that before
it seemed like just do an additional tearing, here we find that
there are these limits after שבעה, shiva, after שלשים. shloshim. Also there's
a position before that by אביו ואמו aviv v'imo you're never allowed
to add to the קרע and here it sounds like after שלשים
shloshim you are. The גמרא at this stage could have said אי
הכי נמי, i hachi nami, by אביו ואמו aviv v'imo you're not
allowed to add, right? So it's a little bit funny what that
answer was. Yeah, I was going to getting back to what you
mentioned earlier about ערי יהודה. arei Yehuda. I was wondering just how
applicable that is today because everything's been rebuilt? Yeah. So basically nowadays
I don't know anybody who does קריעה on ערי יהודה arei Yehuda
to say that those are בחורבנם bechorbanam or on ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I
mean who knows, there might be some. Now the מקדש, Mikdash, when
the מקדש, Mikdash, so there definitely are people that will do קריעה.
Mostly people find a way to get out of it by like
I remember this going back to 30 years ago before first time
I was in Israel was after high school. So the whole trick
we all did was the first time you're going to ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
going to go see the כותל, Kotel, not ירושלים Yerushalayim go to
go see the כותל, Kotel, you borrow somebody else's shirt so you
don't have to do קריעה on it. And then the real trick
was you don't even borrow somebody else's shirt, you say, 'I'll sell
you my shirt.' So then you keep on wearing this shirt, I
say, 'Do you want to buy my shirt for today?' and I'll
keep on wearing it and then I don't have to do קריעה.
Now we're actually going to see that case coming up. But do
you avoid it because it has like something on it now like
it's no longer בחורבנו? bechorbano? I mean like I envision like this.
You mean the הר הבית? Har HaBayit? Well, how is the הר
הבית Har HaBayit less בחורבנה bechorbanah than it was because it has
the because it has the Dome of the Rock? Right. So the
question is is it even worse than it was? Yeah. Alright, so
תנו רבנן. I'm not getting into politics. תנו רבנן, what about ערב
שבת? erev Shabbat? Right, so that was the other thing. If you
go Friday afternoon or שבת, Shabbat, so then you don't do קריעה
then. There are all these tricks of getting out of it. And
then if you make sure to see it within every 30 days,
so it's not like anything. Anyway, but it is true, less and
less I hear people worried about that today. So, I don't know.
I don't know, it seems that that, yeah, I don't know if,
it's a good point, like how much people have mentioned about that.
There's an issue about that, it seems that everyone would demand that
you דאוון *daven* שחרית *shacharis* yourself. Yeah, again, again, as we as
we've asked as we said, we're sort of picking and choosing. תנו
רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*, היוצא *Hayotzei* so actually בבגד קרוע *beveged karua*, if
somebody goes out with a rent garment, it was already rent, לפני
המת *lifnei hamet*, in front of a dead body, הרי זה גוזל
המתים והחיים *harei zeh gozel hametim vehachayim*. You steal from the dead,
you don't give them the right respect because your garment was already
rent, and you're stealing from the living, you're deceiving them, right, גניבת
דעת *gneivat da'at*, you're making it look like you rent your garment
when you did not. So רבן גמליאל אומר *Rabban Gamliel omer*, somebody
who says to his friend, here's this case: השאיליני חלוקך ואלך ואבקר
את אבא שהוא חולה *hashileni chaluqcha ve-elech ve-avaker et abba shehu choleh*.
Now this is not a trick. I mean we sort of I
don't want to skew your interpretation of this. The whole point here
is specifically not a trick. Somebody's father is sick. The question here
is it's taken for granted that a person does not do קריעה
*keriah* if the garment is not his own. But what happens, when
is it implicit when he borrowed it, here he's borrowing the suit,
I'd like to borrow your nice suit, I'm going to go visit
my father. He wasn't borrowing it as a trick, he was borrowing
it so he would look nice when he went to visit his
father. But how much the person lending him was aware that the
father might pass away any moment and therefore was implicitly giving him
permission to do קריעה *keriah* if necessary? So that's the question. Like
if the guy was informing him that I'm going to visit my
father who's on his deathbed and lend me your nice suit, maybe
there's an implicit understanding that if you have to do קריעה *keriah*
you can do קריעה *keriah* on my garment. So let's take a
look. And once he's wearing it, he's got a בעלות *ba'alut* on
the... Well, yes, so that's the... so the reason a person does
not do קריעה *keriah* on a borrowed garment is not like you
don't put ציצית *tzitzis* on a טלית *tallis* that isn't yours because
you have to own it in order to be חייב *chayav* in
ציצית *tzitzis*. It's not like you have to own a garment in
order to be חייב *chayav* to do קריעה *keriah* in it. It's
you're not allowed to do קריעה *keriah* because it's damaging somebody else's
property. So if the person has implicitly acknowledged that you might have
to do that and implicitly allowed you to do that, then you
would do קריעה *keriah*. So let's read the case. Okay. So, אומר
לחבירו השאיליני חלוקך ואלך ואבקר את אבא שהוא חולה *hashileni chaluqcha ve-elech
ve-avaker et abba shehu choleh*, והלך ומצאו שמת *ve-halach umetzau shemet*, and
then he went to visit the father and the father had already
passed away, passed away when he was there, קורע *korea*,
so he does קריעה *keriah* because the guy who lent him the
garment was somewhat aware that that might happen. ומאחה *ume'acho*, but even
though it's a father, he actually now because just because he was
allowed to do the act of קריעה *keriah*, he still has a
responsibility to restore the object as whole of a status as possible.
It's an interesting middle ground. The guy gave him some implicit permission,
but only as limited as possible. So then he does איחוי *ichuy*
which is generally not allowed for a father. וכשבא לביתו מחזיר לו
חלוקו *u-cheshe-bo leveito machzir lo chaluqo*, when he gets home he returns
the garment, ונותן לו דמי קרעו *venoten lo dmei krio*, and pays
for how much it's been depreciated because of the tear, even with
the tear and the repair, it's not like it's never been. So
A, so there was a limited permission, enough to do the act,
but not enough that the person doesn't responsible financially for the cost
or that the person doesn't have to correct it as much as
possible. So that's sort of how what's being interpreted. ואם לא הודיעו
*ve-im lo hodio*, but if he didn't say the circumstances of why
he was borrowing it, הרי זה לא יגע בו *harei zeh lo
yiga bo*, then he can't touch it, it's not his property. Okay,
so quite fascinating like the limited allowance that we're going to interpret
was given there. תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*, חולה שמת לו מת *choleh
shemet lo met*, now this happens quite you know on a not
infrequent basis that people are, you know, a family decides not to
tell somebody about a death, somebody very elderly and you know and
whatever and that the death hearing about a sibling that died let's
say, you know, would be, you know, they figure the person would
not be able to handle the information. So here we have that
situation. חולה שמת לו מת *choleh shemet lo met*, a sick person,
doesn't just mean sick, somebody who's like very deathly ill, and somebody
dies, אין מודיעין אותו *ein modiin oto*, you do not inform, the
הלכה halacha *halacha* is you don't inform the person, obviously you have
to know what the circumstances are, but in because but if the
following concern is present, אין מודיעין אותו שמת שמא תטרף דעתו עליו
*ein modiin oto shemet shema titoraf da'ato alav*, lest it cause him
to be, you know, his mind his emotions disturbed, and that could
actually you know injure his state of health. ואין מקריעין בפניו *ve-ein
mokrin befanav*, and you would not do קריעה *keriah* in his presence
when you go to visit this other, you know, this elderly relative,
you don't have your rent garments on from the fact that you,
you know, you're sitting שבעה shiva *shiva* for somebody else. ומשתיקין את
הנשים מפניו *umeshashtkin et hanashim mipanav*, very interesting sociological phenomenon here, you
keep the women silent, presumably a concern that women would not be
able to handle... no, no, he means the wailers. Oh, you mean
the wailers. Oh, okay. All right, thank you. Thank you for that,
that's better. Okay, ומקרעין לקטן מפני עגמת נפש. mipnei agmat nefesh Now
we're sort of moving away from this person who is sick and
can't find and you want to protect him from this information to
other people. So now let's see, so that's you prevent a deathly
ill person from, or a precariously ill person, from finding out, and
therefore in a way this person isn't sitting שבעה shiva, even though
they technically should be, but it's more important to protect them from
that information. And now somewhat in the reverse, a minor who's not
obligated to do observances of שבעה, shiva, you still do קריעה for
the קטן, katan, meaning on the קטן's katan garments מפני עגמת נפש
because it leads to a distressed soul, meaning in what's normally explained
as not for the קטן katan but for everybody else that it
just makes it that much more tragic. וקורעין על חמיו ועל חמותו
מפני כבוד אשתו. vekorin al hamiv veal hamoto mipnei kavod ishto. And
now so here also mourning practices that either the first one is
not being done when it's in a way halachically was obligated, and
here being done when it's not fully obligated. So a person would
go ahead and do קריעה for his father-in-law and mother-in-law, again all
this said from the male perspective but obviously true for the female
as well, מפני כבוד אשתו mipnei kavod ishto out of respect for
his wife. What? להלכה lehalacha I don't think we do this. So
אמר רב פפא תנא באבל רבתי, amar Rav Papa tana beAvel Rabbati,
we taught in אבל רבתי Avel Rabbati which is in מסכת שמחות,
Masechet Semachot, אדם לא יניח תינוק בתוך חיקו, adam lo yaniach tinok
betoch heiko, a person should not put an infant in his lap
מפני שמביאו לידי שחוק, mipnei shemevio lidei schok, it leads him to
sort of laughing, ונמצא מתגנה על הבריות, venimtza mitganeh al habriyot, and
that causes him to be seen unseemly in the eyes of other
people. What are you doing? You're supposed to be sitting שבעה, here
you are, you're playing around, you're laughing. It's actually a funny, it's
an interesting הלכה which people grapple with because first of all, what
if it's the person's own kid? What if it's for an act
of comfort, not an act of playing around, but there's something comforting
about that? So in different situations people treat this more or less
in absolute terms. I mean what I've tended to see is people
might for a minute take you know, but not overly do this.
But again this is something that people find challenging, but the גמרא
gives a specific reason about שחוק schok and מתגנה mitganeh and so
on, and one wonders if different contexts would make that different. Let's
try to just read to the bottom of the page so we
won't be more than a דף behind. ואין מברין אלא על מיטות
זקופות. ve'ein mavrin ela al mitot zkufot. Now when it comes time
to give that first meal after the cemetery,
it is not done on upright beds but on overturned bed,
excuse me, ואין מברין אלא על מיטות זקופות, ve'ein mavrin ela al
mitot zkufot, only on upright beds. And the question of course here
is, is the context during חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? I mentioned to
you that question in the משנה mishna and therefore the beds are
not upturned, they're in their right position, or is the context even
in general? It's not clear. Let's read what the גמרא says. תנו
רבנן ההולך לבית האבל אם היה לבו גס בו, haholech lebeit ha'avel
im haya libo gas bo, a person goes to the house of
a mourner if he's very comfortable with him, meaning very intimate and
friendly, יברוהו על מיטות כפויות. yavruhu al mitot kfuyot.
So then the אבל avel sits on an upturned bed and the
person feeding the אבל, avel, this is the first meal after the
cemetery or maybe even the first day, sits together with him on
an upturned bed and feeds him in sort of an acceptable intimacy
even though they're both on the upturned bed. ואם לאו, ve'im lav,
but if he doesn't feel comfortable with him,
יברוהו על מיטות זקופות, yavruhu al mitot zkufot, the bed
should be in its upright position. Now the question is, are they
both on upright couches? If it's not חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, again
if it's חול המועד Chol HaMoed then regardless of if you feel
comfortable or not it should be upright couches. If it's not חול
המועד, Chol HaMoed, so then it might mean that the אבל avel
is on an upturned bed and the person that's not so intimate
and comfortable with the אבל avel should be on the bed in
the upright position. רבא איתרע ביה מילתא, Rava itra beih milta, רבא
Rava had a death in the family. על לגביה אבא בר מרתא,
al lgabeih Abba bar Marta, so אבא בר מרתא Abba bar Marta
came to visit him, דהוא אבא בר מניומי. dehu Abba bar Minyumi.
רבא זקיף, Rava zakif, so רבא Rava was on an upright bed.
אבא בר מרתא כפי Abba bar Marta kefi and אבא בר מרתא,
Abba bar Marta, who wasn't the אבל, avel, was the one feeding
רבא Rava was on an upturned bed. So אמר, amar, so רבא
Rava said כמה לית ביה דעתא להאי צורבא מרבנן, kama leit beih
da'ata lehai tzurba merabbanan, how much does this rabbinic student not have?
He doesn't know what he's doing. He's on an upturned bed and
the אבל's avel on an upright bed. Now what was רבא Rava
doing on an upright bed? Again we might be talking about חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. It's a major debate in the ראשונים how to
read this. But whatever it was, the fact that the מנחם menachem
was on the upturned bed when the אבל avel was on the
upright bed clearly said what does he know? He doesn't even know
what he's doing. Okay, we will I guess pick up with this
tomorrow.